<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "oats_vospace_users_guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
                The VOSpace is the IVOA interface to distributed storage. 
It specifies how Virtual Observatory agents and applications can use network 
attached data stores to persist and exchange data in a standard way.
        </para>
        <para>
Users want to be able to easily publish and share their own data as well as 
have data reside close to computation nodes when large-scale processing or 
dynamic caches for intermediate data products in workflows are involved.
There are many storage solutions available, so the astronomer community
does not invent a new one, but specify a lightweight interface, VOSpace, 
that sits on top of existing storage solutions, providing a common 
interface to an underlying heterogeneity of implementations from local 
file systems to bulk data grids. VOSpace can distinguish between 
unstructured data, which is just a collection of bytes, and structured 
data where there is knowledge about how the bytes are arranged and so 
additional operations are possible. Individual VOSpace instances can 
also be federated into a peer network so that the user just interacts
with a single data space. 
        </para>
        <para>
A VOSpace web service is an access point for a distributed storage 
network. Through this access point, a client can:
        </para>
<itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
      <para>
        add or delete data objects in a tree data structure
      </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
      <para>
        manipulate metadata for the data objects
      </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
      <para>
         obtain URIs through which the content of the data objects can be accessed
      </para>
   </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
        <para>
VOSpace does not define how the data is stored or transferred, only the 
control messages to gain access. Thus, the VOSpace interface can readily 
be added to an existing storage system.
        </para>
        <para>
Each data object within a VOSpace service is represented as a node and 
has a description called a representation. A useful analogy to have in 
mind when reading this document is that a node is equivalent to a file.
        </para>
        <para>
Nodes in VOSpace have unique identifiers expressed as URIs in the `vos' 
scheme, as defined below.
        </para>
        <para>
In the CADC open software repository (https://github.com/opencadc)
a VOSpace service client command line is available. This guide explains 
how to download and run this client and the available commands. Examples are provided.
        </para>

	<section id="sect-Requirements">
		<title>Requirements and recomendations</title>
                <para>
                Prerequisites and recomendations to run the Credential Delegation Service are: 
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
		        <para>
	        	Centos 7 Operative System is recommended,	
		        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                        Java 7 or higher installed
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

	</section>

</chapter>

